Previously on Shogun.
Now are you ready
to do your part?
I'm ready.
I am leaving tomorrow.
You forget your manners!
Unless we are confined here.
No one is confined here.
It's true we are all being
kept here against our will.
I cannot live with the offense.
Your permits.
Behold, the great warlord who
tricked his own loyal vassals
into a noiseless smothering.
A message from Lord Ishido.
Your offer of service
instead of death
he accepts.
They've infiltrated the castle.
We should go to the gate!
I will not risk being captured.
It's Ishido
he'll never let us leave alive.
Mariko-sama!
Nigel!
He's gonna hear us.
I'm being quiet.
Who's gonna know?
Look at it. It looks sharp.
Be quiet. He'll hear you.
I'm only going to look.
Mother's going to get angry
if she knows we're in here.
Be careful.
Why is it chipped?
Because Grandfather used it to fight
off a whole army of Japanese assassins.
Was it really given
to you by a savage?
Anjin!
Get up!
Mariko-sama.
Mariko-sama!
Heavenly Father,
we commit to you your
loyal servant, Mariko-sama.
Mariko-sama, Mariko-sama.
Lady Mariko!
Forgive me...
All of this was
tragic and avoidable.
Osaka Castle isn't as safe
as we were led to believe
that much is clear.
Lady Mariko should have been
allowed to leave
without incident.
What does it matter now.
A letter of protest
from my brother.
The violent death
of his prized vassal
has left him shocked.
He has fled Edo in secret
and prepares for war.
This means nothing.
Whether he surrenders here
or in battle is up to him.
What matters is we are united.
To think this
dishonorable attack
could have been ordered by
a member of this Council...
Such a despicable attack.
Only Toranaga is conniving
enough to pull it off.
He's trying to sow
division between us.
It is our duty to
end his threat.
I say
we march.
Lady Mariko must first be
given a Christian burial.
I am sorry for Mariko's death,
but let us not forget
she was Akechi.
The same line that murdered
Lady Ochiba's father.
Lady Mariko will
generously
be honored.
Fine.
In that case, we'll
go to war after.
And with the Heir's support.
Of course.
His banners make
our side lawful,
and Toranaga's unlawful.
And what will be done
about the heretic?
After we vote for war,
what happens to him is no
longer of interest to me.
War is inevitable.
Inevitable.
This matter...
Perhaps it requires
a bit more debate.
Stop this superstition.
We're not peasants, digging
in the dirt for meaning.
We are protectors of the Realm.
The vote is done.
You look well.
Your hearing... is it improving?
Ears.
Thank you.
I thought Lady Mariko
would only be captured.
She resisted, and she died.
There was nothing we could do.
Your efforts will
not be forgotten.
After Toranaga is gone,
your seat on the
Council is secured.
The strangest thing...
When the Taikō was about
to go to war with Toranaga,
he had all the votes
until that earthquake hit.
It was a big one
beneath Lake Biwa.
His allies called it a bad omen.
The Taikō was forced
to forge a peace.
That was long ago.
Where is it?
He blamed the catfish.
Its thick, ugly tail
shaking the earth.
Yabushige. Yabushige!
There are no catfish
in that pond.
Ah...
Of course I know that.
Return to Izu.
Gather your army.
Wait for my command.
Huh?
I return you to the sky.
Bear many daughters.
Was it really given
to you by a savage?
We live and we die.
You've been asleep
a long time...
Lady Mariko was
buried the other day.
Get up. Time to leave.
Lord Kiyama's men will
escort you to the harbor.
Well, get it over with then.
You have been permitted to
return to Toranaga-sama's galley.
Here is your pass.
Why am I receiving this
permission from Lord Kiyama?
Where is Yabushige-sama?
He's preparing the galley in Osaka
Bay. I have come to bring you to him.
All families have now
been released from Osaka.
Praise be to God. At least
that crisis is behind us.
Toranaga won't be surrendering.
Not yet.
Ishido-sama has mobilized the
Council of Regents to war.
The Lady Ochiba has
pledged her son's support.
Toranaga will be dead in weeks.
Then you don't know
Yoshii Toranaga.
The hostages are free.
Got just what he wanted.
No dirty hands, no war.
Just a woman.
She can't have heard me before
before she died.
I spoke before God.
Not your God or my God.
Just God.
Do you think it was acceptable?
Rest assured she was
already sanctified.
Before her death, she came to
me and received absolution.
I think it would've pleased
her to see us being civil.
Yes. Yes, you may be right.
Perhaps there might come a time
we can set aside our differences.
Yes.
All this nonsense.
Catholic and Protestant, and
Calvinist and every other shitist.
It's only a shame that
day will never come.
Will it, Father?
Is this where I'm
to be ambushed?
Like the last time
I tried to leave.
No longer protected.
Is that how I
finally meet my end?
I will not deny it.
You were meant to
die in these woods.
But an arrangement was made.
You will leave Osaka alive.
You'll have to forgive me
if I'm having some trouble
accepting anything on your word.
On this, you will
just have to trust me.
Go with God, Anjin-sama.
It was Lady Maria.
She asked the Church to spare
your life before she died.
And now I have.
I have kept my word to her.
Goodbye.
And good luck.
What does it mean, "on
a leafless branch"?
It was written by my friend.
The one who was just buried?
Yes.
So we must finish the poem.
What line would you write next?
Well
a branch can have fruit
also flowers...
How about...
Flowers are only flowers
because they fall.
But thankfully, the wind.
We should never
have gone to Osaka.
Your ship.
We could sail on it together.
To your home country.
What's your country called?
- Country.
- Country, yes. What is it?
England.
Take me there.
Don't you understand?
Here, then...
Teach me how to dive.
Like you taught Toranaga.
Show me.
Huh? Pull yourself
together, man.
What are you saying? Hurry!
Look!
Omi!
I'm sorry...
Lord Yabushige...
I'm instructed to
ask for your swords.
My swords.
These men belong to Lord
Toranaga, our liege lord.
The orders also belong to him.
Of course.
This way.
Enemies slipped past our
guards by cover of night.
They knew exactly
where to strike.
Christians, we think.
It's all so terrible...
Enemies? Christians did this?
Mariko-sama.
Come this way!
Please stop.
Until we find those who
aided the Christian raiders,
no one in this
village will rest.
Lord Toranaga has ordered it.
Lord.
Thank you for returning my
consorts and my vassals.
You've heard the news
that Lady Mariko is dead.
Yes, I know.
That night,
you were seen letting
intruders into my quarters.
One of Mariko's ladies-in-waiting
was with you in the cellar.
She sent a letter to Omi.
After Lady Mariko's death,
they say you were guilt-stricken
and asked for forgiveness.
I felt it was my duty
to alert our lord.
Did you aid this attack?
Yes I did.
Fine.
All of your lands are forfeit.
Please slit your belly
by sunset tomorrow.
Lord...
If you must kill me,
give me a good death!
Like being torn apart by cannon
or eaten alive by a
school of angry fish.
I beg you! Please!
Fine suggestions, but
I don't trust you.
Please commit seppuku
by sunset tomorrow.
Izu is the fief of
the Kashigi clan.
I declare Omi to be my heir,
and request it be given to him.
It is fair to ask, but Izu
is no longer yours to give.
Who would you like
to second your death?
Let it be the Anjin.
No.
In that case,
I would be honored if
it would be you, Lord.
I shall.
Until tomorrow, then.
May Fudō Myō'ō
smile on tomorrow.
Hmm.
Fuji...
You look
healthy and strong.
Thank you.
No translator.
You protected my new son.
I am grateful to all of you.
So many have been lost
since we parted in Osaka.
Beginning with Lord Nagakado,
whom we still mourn.
Thankfully I have more sons,
because of you.
The morning we
left Osaka Castle,
this came in secret
from Lady Ochiba.
Have you read it?
What a suggestion!
If I could use words
like scattering flowers
and falling leaves,
what a bonfire my
poems would make.
Those words are too
beautiful to belong to you.
They belong to Lady Mariko.
Only her words
remain with us now.
But what a bonfire she made.
What is that?
They carry remains of my
husband, Lord Tadayoshi,
and my only son Tsurumaru.
I should bury them
in the family temple,
but I wish to be close to them.
I'm not sure what to do...
Anjin-sama.
Tomorrow I am leaving.
Lord Toranaga has given me
permission to become a nun.
Do you understand what I say?
"Nun"?
Fuji, nun?
Yes.
Nun.
I wish
for you to stay.
Impossible.
I order it.
Fuji is
consort.
So sorry,
but I am no longer your consort.
My service to Lord
Toranaga is now complete.
Well, you served him well.
Fuji
best nun.
I will try.
However...
I am sad for this village.
Ajiro.
After what happened
to your ship,
the villagers are being
severely punished.
I am sad too.
Fuji.
Prepare message
for Lord Toranaga.
Wish to see him tomorrow.
Your sword and your gun.
I will bring you
to Lord Toranaga.
Tell him
we are disgusted by the
destruction of his ship.
My men will not rest until
the saboteur is found.
Lord, perhaps this is too much for
a simple fisherman to translate.
Does he still not know?
Tell him.
Forgive me for the
deception, Anjin-dono.
I was born Tonomoto Akinao,
in the Azuchi prefecture.
I am samurai.
In order to spy on his enemies,
years ago, my lord ordered me to convert
to the religion of the Portuguese.
So I took the name
Muraji and moved here.
Well at least
you're not Catholic.
I am a Christian and also
I am Tonomoto Akinao,
vassal to Toranaga-sama.
I am both these things.
My lord says he will not rest
until he finds those who
helped destroy your ship.
Muraji,
I've prepared something
to say in Japanese.
Perhaps you will
help me if I falter.
Thank you for
agreeing to see me.
The day you surrendered
to your brother...
I apologize for my disrespect.
Back then, I had
given up
that...
"Hope"?
Hope.
Or is the word you are
looking for "faith"?
At this point, either
one of them will do.
Please leave Ajiro alone.
One man lost hope,
but Ajiro is loyal.
Why does he care about
the plight of my village?
Doesn't he seek
vengeance on his enemies?
He asks why you do not
wish to fight your enemies.
My enemies didn't burn my ship.
He says it was not his
enemies who burned the ship.
It was Mariko-sama. She hated
my war against the Catholics.
He says it was Lady Mariko...
She hated his war with
the Christians in Japan.
So she made an
arrangement in Osaka
to trade my survival for
the destruction of my ship.
She ordered the destruction of
his ship in exchange for his life.
So you see?
This death, not right.
Want no more blood.
What about the Anjin's war?
I don't need it anymore.
My war
small war.
I refuse his request.
Why?
Those who are disloyal to me continue
to breathe air in my domain...
I cannot just stand by.
He says the sentence stays until
the disloyal have been found.
What are you doing?
I was the disloyal one.
I die,
not village.
Who do you think you are?
Does he really think that
if he takes his own life
I would stop searching
for these traitors?
I die,
not village.
No.
Don't you understand?
I came here to use you.
To use you!
From the day I set
foot on your shores,
I fed you shit.
"Enemy."
Enemy!
Fuck it.
We live and we die.
I, Anjin, by my death
protest the callous punishment of
this village by Yoshii Toranaga.
Enough!
If you're finally done,
rebuild that ship,
and make me a fleet.
Find a good husband for my wife.
Make sure he's not an idiot.
You made me your heir...
I'm grateful.
Uncle...
I swear the name of Kashigi
is safe in my hands.
If I didn't think so, I
wouldn't have suggested it.
I considered you
the son I never had.
My death poem.
My dead body,
Don't burn it, Don't bury it,
Just leave it in the field.
And with it, fill the
belly of some hungry dog.
Impressive, right?
I think my skills have
never been sharper.
I have learned much from you.
And now the learning ends.
My final will.
Have a good death.
I'm sorry to say it goes
no further than this.
My nephew will make
a good vassal to you.
You'll be lucky to have him.
I have you to thank for that.
And the Anjin.
You have me to
thank for him too.
If only I could have
lived to see it...
The day your plan comes
together, whatever it is...
My nephew's first battle...
When the Anjin sails against
the Christians who
burned his ship...
So many days I could have seen.
If only it were that simple.
The ship had to be destroyed.
It was between that
and the Anjin's life.
Appointing a watchman
to spread gunpowder
wasn't that hard.
Mariko negotiated for
the Church, and I agreed.
You burned that ship.
It was a necessary
ruse to test the Anjin.
Perhaps someday I'll
tell him the truth.
By then he'll have
rebuilt the ship,
and I'll likely have
to destroy it again.
I don't think it's his
fate to ever leave Japan.
How does it feel
to shape the wind to your will?
I don't control the wind.
I only study it.
But how can you win this?
With your forces outnumbered,
the Heir's army
about to attack...
Is it Crimson Sky?
I suppose it could work,
but I don't see how.
At least tell me before I die...
Yabushige.
After all we've been through,
I thought you of all
people would see.
Crimson Sky is already finished.
With the Regents united,
I could never send
an army to Osaka.
It would have meant
certain death.
So I sent a woman to do
what an army never could.
Don't you see
what's coming next?
In just one month,
we will meet our
enemies at Sekigahara.
Five armies squaring off
on the field of battle.
And you're right...
With the Heir's army on
Ishido's side, I'd be finished.
However,
because of Mariko's actions,
Lady Ochiba has grown tired
of her alliance with Ishido.
In a letter to me,
she secretly pledged
to keep the Heir's army
from the battlefield.
On that day, Ishido
will have no banner.
The Regents will turn on
him before a sword is drawn.
Only then will my
dream be realized...
I will start it in Edo,
my center of power.
A nation without wars.
An era of great peace.
All of us have
made this possible.
You, me,
Lady Mariko...
Even the barbarian who
came out of the sea.
How many times I've thought of
giving his life away, but stopped.
Not because he's important
my banner would
survive without him,
but because he makes me laugh.
And my enemies
need a distraction.
It's hypocrisy,
our lives...
All this death and
sacrifice from lesser men
just to ensure some
victory in our names...
Do you remember what the
Anjin said on the day we met,
when I told him his
fight was pointless?
"Unless I win."
If you win, anything
is possible.
Even Shōgun.
It's what you've always
wanted, isn't it?
You're no better than us,
in your secret heart...
Tell me the truth.
I'll take it to my grave.
Why tell a dead man the future?
Are you to row me
to my convent...?
Fuji-sama, you've
served me all this time.
Please just allow me
this one final gesture.
Look.
Come.
To sea.
Last thing I ask.
I've always been of the mind
that a soul committed to the deep
is a soul who, in some way,
lives on forever within it.
Understand?
Together... forever.
Together forever.
Let your hands be
the last to hold her.
Raise the ropes!
Hoist the lines.
I know you're tired, but tide's
come up some, so we'll try again.
There you go.
Wait for my cue.
Pull!
Oh. We're pissing in the wind.
We need more water. Uh,
tell them they can rest.
Take a break.
Right.
Yes. Yes, this is wonderful.
Raise the ropes!
Raise the lines.
Right, you miserable,
sniveling, festering shit rags.
I have a feeling
this is the one.
Listen, everyone...
No. Look, Muraji. Just keep
that between you and I, huh?
Pull!
There she is!
I told you she was beautiful! I told
you she'd be worth the business!
That's enough. That's enough.
Good job!
Thank you.
Great work today.
Hmm.