Behold the great warlord,
who tricked his
own loyal vassals
into a noiseless smothering.
Mariko-sama!
- Nigel!
- Shh!
They'll hear us.
I'm being quiet.
Look at it.
It looks sharp.
Be quiet. They'll hear you.
I'm only going to look.
Mother's going to get angry
if she knows we're in here.
Be careful.
Why is it chipped?
Because Grandfather used it
to fight off a whole army
of Japanese assassins.
Was it really given
to you by a savage?
Mariko-sama.
Mariko-sama!
Heavenly Father,
we commit to you,
your loyal servant...
Mariko-sama.
Yabushige-dono! Yabushige-dono!
Was it really given to you
by a savage?
We live,
and we die.
Well, get it over with, then.
You have been
permitted to return
to Toranaga-sama's galley.
Here is your pass.
Why am I receiving
this permission
from Lord Kiyama?
Where is Yabushige-sama?
He is preparing the
galley in Osaka Bay.
I have come to bring you to him.
All families have now
been released from Osaka.
Praise be to God, at least
that crisis is behind us.
Toranaga won't be surrendering.
Not yet.
Ishido-sama has mobilized the
Council of Regents to war.
The Lady Ochiba has
pledged her son's support.
Toranaga will be dead in weeks.
Then you don't know.
Yoshii Toranaga.
The hostages are free.
He got just what he wanted.
No dirty hands, no war.
Just a woman.
She couldn't have
heard me... before.
Before she died, I
spoke before God.
Not your God or my God
just God.
Do you think it was acceptable?
Rest assured she was
already sanctified.
Before her death, she came to
me and received absolution.
I think it would
have pleased her
to see us being civil.
Yes.
Yes, you may be right.
Perhaps there
might come a time
we can set aside
our differences.
Yes.
All this nonsense.
Catholic and Protestant
and Calvinist
and every other shitist.
It's only a shame that
day will never come.
Will it, Father?
Is this where I'm
to be ambushed,
like the last time
I tried to leave?
No longer protected.
Is that how I
finally meet my end?
I will not deny it,
you were meant to
die in these woods.
But an arrangement was made.
You will leave Osaka alive.
You'll have to forgive me
if I'm having some trouble
accepting anything on your word.
On this, you will
just have to trust me.
Go with God, Anjin-sama.
It was Lady Maria.
She asked the Church
to spare your life
before she died.
And now I have...
I have kept my word to her.
Goodbye.
And good luck.
England.
Pull yourself together, man.
Enemies? Christians did this?
Mariko-sama.
Hmm.
What is that?
Anjin-sama...
Yes.
Well, you served him well.
Forgive me for the
deception, Anjin-dono.
I was born Tonomoto Akinao,
in the Azuchi Prefecture.
I am samurai.
In order to spy on his enemies,
years ago, my lord ordered
me to convert to the religion
of the Portuguese, so
I took the name Muraji
and moved here.
Well, at least
you're not Catholic.
I am a Christian, and also,
I am Tonomoto Akinao,
vassal to Toranaga-sama.
I am both these things.
My lord says he will not rest
until he finds those who
helped destroy your ship.
Muraji...
I've prepared something
to say in Japanese.
Perhaps you will
help me if I falter.
Hope. Or is the word you
are looking for "faith"?
At this point,
either one will do.
He asks why you do not
wish to fight your enemies.
My enemies didn't burn my ship.
It was Mariko-sama.
She hated my war
against the Catholics.
So she made an
arrangement in Osaka
to trade my survival
for the destruction of my ship.
So, you see?
I don't need it anymore.
He says the sentence
stays until the disloyal
have been found.
I was the disloyal one.
Don't you understand?
I came here to use you.
To use you!
From the day I set
foot on your shores,
I fed you shit.
I fed you... shit.
Fuck it.
We live and we die.
Ah.
Fuji-sama, you've
served me all this time.
Please just allow me
this one final gesture.
Look.
I've always been of
the mind that a soul
committed to the
deep is a soul who,
in some way,
lives on forever within it.
Hai.
Raise the ropes!
I know you're tired, but
tide's come up some,
so we'll try again.
There you go.
We're pissing in the wind.
We need more water.
Tell them they can rest.
Right.
Yes.
Yes, this is wonderful.
Raise the ropes!
Right, you miserable, sniveling
festering shit rags!
- I have a feeling this is the one!
- Ah.
No! No, no, Muraji.
Just, uh, keep that
between you and I.
There she is!
I told you she was beautiful!
I told you she'd be
worth the blisters!
That's enough! That's enough.
Hmm.
Captioned by Media Access
Group at WGBH access.wgbh.org